是, 大臣  第3季第6集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译&校对&时间轴: tpring
知易行难
("丘吉尔在野生涯")
他什么时候来?
What time is he coming?
随时会来 早该到了
Any time. Should be here now.
也许他出事了
Perhaps something’s happened to him.
你说他误了公交车?
You think he's missed his bus?
不不不
No, no, no.
我是说他可能遇到些...事
I mean something may have... happened.
他到底是什么人?
Who is he, exactly?
我只知道他是陆军军官 有事告诉我
All I know is he's an army officer with something to tell me
电话里不便明说
he wouldn't divulge on the phone.
估计没多大事      可能吧
it’s probably nothing. Perhaps.
记得"丘吉尔在野生涯"里说的吗?
Remember Churchill, the wilderness years?
他得知陆军无法抵御希特勒的事
He found out about our military inadequacy
就是听军官说的
from army officers.
所以他在野期间 还能朝媒体漏消息
So in the wilderness he could leak stories to the press
让政府难堪 我也能
and embarrass the government. I could do that!
可你在政府里啊
But you're in the government.
哦 对
Oh, yes!
我去开
I'll get it.
桑德斯少校?      是 先生
Major Saunders? Yes, sir.
进来
Come in.
跟上
Follow me.
没事 我夫人 安妮      晚上好
it’s all right. My wife, Annie. Good evening.
喝点吗?      谢谢
Drink? Thanks.
威士忌?      谢谢
Scotch? Thanks.
请坐      谢谢
Sit down. Thanks.
不必多礼      谢谢 我是说 抱歉
No need to keep thanking me. Thanks. I mean, sorry.
也不必抱歉      抱歉 我是说 谢谢
No need to apologise, either. Sorry. I mean, thanks.
你们谈话要我回避吗?      请留下 你不介意的话
Shall I let you talk in private? Stay if that's Ok with you.
对 不用瞒安妮 我什么都告诉她
Yes. No secrets from Annie. I tell her everything.
一般反复说几遍
Several times, usually!
那么这是高度机密?      对 确实是
So, is this highly confidential? It is, rather, yes.
要开收音机吗?      有什么好节目吗?
Shall I turn on the radio? Is there something good on?
以防我们被窃听      有这可能吗?
In case we're being bugged. Oh. is that likely?
谁负责窃听政客?
Who's in charge Of bugging politicians?
对 想起来了 是我
Yes, come to think of it, I am!
那就没事了
That's all right, then.
我能不能说 我告诉您的事
Could I say that what I'm about to tell you
是以私人身份说的?
I'm telling you on a personal basis?
好吧 具体什么意思?
Fine... What do you mean, exactly?
我是私下告诉您
I'm telling you personally
不是告诉行政事务大臣
and not as Minister for Administrative Affairs.
可我就是行政事务大臣
But I am Minister of Administrative Affairs.
但我告诉的不是那个您
But I'm not telling you in that role.
而是新闻工作者
I'm telling you as a journalist.
新闻工作者? 你不是陆军军官嘛
Journalist? I thought you were an army officer?
不 您作为新闻工作者      我是大臣
No, you're a journalist. I'm a minister.
对 可你当大臣之前呢?
But what were you before you became a minister?
你出道的本钱 不是赏你的
Your starter for ten, no conferring!
对 我明白了
I get your drift.
你是说你跟我说的
You're telling me what you're telling me,
尽管我不知道你要说什么
though I don't know yet what you're telling me,
是说给"改革"杂志的前主编 是吗?
as the former editor of “Reform".
对 您是个好主编
Yes. You were a very fine editor.
我不能这么说      你经常这么说
I wouldn't say that. You've often said that!
可怎么防止作为大臣的我
But how do I prevent myself, as a minister,
得知你告诉作为主编的我的消息呢?
from knowing what you'll tell me as a former editor?
我没法不让大臣知道
I can't prevent the minister from knowing.
我想他是说 这是头衔问题      好吧
He means it’s a question of hats. Yes.
我今晚不顶大臣头衔
I'm not wearing my ministerial hat tonight,
但我得警告你
but I ought to warn you,
如果我有必要知道这件事
If I need to be told what you tell me,
我会义无反顾地告诉我自己
I shan't hesitate in my duty to keep myself informed!
好吧 谁负责
Fine. Now, who's in charge
英国军火出口?
of selling British weapons to foreigners?
抢答 哈克 伦敦政经学院      闭嘴
Bzzz. Hacker, LSE. Shut up, Annie.
您曾经在"改革"上撰文
You wrote an article in "Reform" about the sale
抨击英国政府乱卖军火
of British weapons to undesirable foreigners.
对 那篇文章叫 "可怕的交易"
Yes, it was called "The Dreadful Trade".
为我们自己和盟友生产军火纯属爱国之举
Patriotic to manufacture arms for our own defence.
尽管有些盟友不大可爱
Although not all our allies are very commendable.
但我们绝不能把军火
But we must not sell weapons
卖给暴政国家 纳粹独裁者
to bolster the regimes of foreign despots, Nazi dictators...
或者恐怖分子      对 恐怖分子...恐怖分子?
Or terrorists. Terroris... Terrorists?
恐怖分子 我说过我刚从罗马回来
Terrorists. As I told you, I've recently returned from Rome.
对 北约是吗?      对 赴北约军事代表团
NATO, wasn't it? A military delegation to NATO.
在那里 他们给我看了一些
While I was there, they showed me something
恐怖分子总部缴获的东西
they'd captured in a raid on a terrorist HQ.
一台电子炸弹引爆器
It was a computerised bomb detonator.
非常新 非常秘密 非常致命
Very new, very secret, and very lethal.
谁给你看的?      恐怕我不能说 这是机密
Who showed it to you? I can't possibly say. it’s a confidence.
好吧 电子炸弹引爆器?
I see. Computerised bomb detonator?
对 可以设置来测量目标体重
You set it to calculate the weight of the victim,
车速 确保弹无虚发
speed of his car, so you're sure to get him,
设好之后 用雷达还可以遥控
and you can reprogram it remotely, by radio, after setting it.
天 真没想到意大利人也懂这种高科技
Gosh. I don't associate Italians with that sort of technology!
不是意大利产的 是这里产的
It wasn’t made in Italy. It was made here.
英国制造?
Made in Britain?
对 国防部下的订单 英国纳税人的出钱
Defence contract and paid for by the British taxpayer.
意大利恐怖分子在用?      正是
And used by Italian terrorists? Yes.
他们哪来的?      我就是问这个
Where did they get them? That's what I want to know.
没跟别人说过吧?
You haven't told anybody else?
我不能 如果我正式上报 就得透露消息来源
If I make an official report, I have to disclose my sources.
可如果我告诉接近政府高层的人...
But if I tell someone near the top of government...
呃 其实就是政府高层
Er, at the top, actually.
对 告诉他英国秘密武器给了意大利恐怖分子
British equipment was being supplied to Italian terrorists,
他就会...      当然
then he would, er... Absolutely.
他会怎样?
What would he?
查出怎么回事
Find out how it’s being done.
调查必须由英国政府高层发起
The investigation would have to start in Britain at the top level.
好
Fine.
可你说你是私下告诉我
But you told me you were telling me on a personal level.
对 可您私下知道了 就算没正式知道
Yes, but now you know personally, if not officially,
您也可以用私人消息
you can use your personal knowledge
展开正式调查
to start official investigations
以正式查证来打消私人疑虑
to get official confirmation of personal suspicions
所以您私下 而不是正式知道的
so what you now know personally, but not officially,
届时就能正式知道 也私下知道了
you will then know officially as well as personally.
你该不会是汉弗莱爵士家亲戚吧?
You're not related to Sir Humphrey Appleby by any chance?
谁?      算了
Who? Never mind!
我就是觉得有必要告诉谁      当然
I felt I had to tell someone. Absolutely.
好 现在我知道了 私下的
Well, now I know, personally.
太妙了 您会采取些措施吧?
Marvellous. Gong to do something about it, aren't you?
当然 绝对要采取      马上?
Absolutely, indeed I am. Right away?
马上
Right away.
您要采取什么措施?
What are you gong to do?
我会好好考虑你的消息 马上
I'm gong to think about what you've told me. Right away.
然后呢?
And then?
然后会考虑许多对策
Then I will consider various courses of action.
毫不含糊      您要毫不含糊地采取对策
Without delay. You'll take action without delay.
我要毫不含糊地开始考虑对策
I will consider taking action without delay.
你不是汉弗莱爵士家亲戚吧?
Are you related to Sir Humphrey Appleby?
再来一杯?      不了 我得走了
Like another drink? No, I must be off.
能信得过您来处理这件可怕的事吧
Can I rely on you to tackle this shocking matter?
尽管放心
Indeed you can.
再见      晚安
Goodbye. Goodnight.
晚安 少校 谢谢      晚安 先生
Goodnight, Major. Goodnight, sir.
你怎么看?      你会采取措施吧?
What do you think? You'll do something?
我当然会 如果应该的话
I certainly will, if it’s right.
但我不能相信这会是真的
But I can't believe it’s true.
可能是真的吗?
Could it happen?
不可能吧 可能吗?
Couldn't. Could it?
不光不应该 而且不可能
It's not just that it shouldn't. It couldn't.
就算可能 也不应该 应该是吧
And if it could, it wouldn’t. Would it?
你还真是汉弗莱爵士家亲戚
You are related to Sir Humphrey Appleby!
汉弗莱 有件事我必须跟你谈
Humphrey, I must talk to you about something
这事我非常忧心
which concerns me deeply.
确实事关重大
Really profoundly important.
您是说政府部门库存控制
The amendment to the order on stock control
通则修正案?
in government establishments?
那是开发区地方政府租约
The procedure for renewal of local authority leaseholds
延期程序?
in development areas?
不 我担心的是关系到人命的大问题
No, what concerns me is a great issue really of life and death.
哦 这个不该工作时间谈吧?
Shouldn't that wait till after work?
这就是工作      真的? 那请说
It is work. Really? Please go on.
英国军工企业是怎样
How do British armaments manufacturers
向外国出口武器的?
sell their arms to foreigners?
我想是先从经贸部申领出口许可证
You get an export licence from the Department of Trade.
私营企业也能出口军火?
Private firms can sell their arms abroad?
通过行业和政府中介      卖给谁?
Companies and government agencies. To whom?
一般是外国政府      没别人?
Foreign governments, usually. Is that all?
有时候也卖给军火商 二道贩子
Well, sometimes you can sell to an arms dealer, third party.
一个曼城人可能代表海峡群岛某个集团
A man in Manchester buys on behalf of Channel Islands
合同订立于卢森堡...
with contacts in Luxembourg...
没法真正控制终端用户是谁吗?
There's no real control over who the arms go to in the end?
有的 军火商必须出具终端用户证书
Indeed there is. The dealer has to provide an end user certificate
得有政府承认的签字
which is a signature acceptable to the government
证明最终顾客有使用授权
that the ultimate customer Is an approved user.
真的有保障吗?
Is that a real guarantee?
你能不能料到一艘英国航母
Would you be surprised if a British aircraft carrier
在中非共和国出现?
turned up in the Central African Republic?
大臣 这我还真料不到
I, for one, would be very surprised.
那里距海一千英里呢
It's 1,000 miles inland!
你懂我的意思 小型武器呢?
You know what I mean. What about smaller weapons?
官方绝对禁止的 有严格安全措施
It's officially impossible. Stringent security,
严密的检查手续 还有仔细的复查
rigorous inspections, meticulous scrutiny.
那就是烟幕弹啰?
You mean it’s all a facade?
这个讨论到此为止吧 大臣?
I think this conversation should end here.
不行 正如我所料
No, it’s as I thought.
昨晚 一个机密线人向我透露
A confidential source has disclosed to me
英国军火被卖给了意大利恐怖分子
that British arms are being sold to Italian terrorists.
这样啊 请问哪位机密线人?
I see. May I ask who this confidential source was?
汉弗莱 我说了是机密
Humphrey, I said it was confidential.
抱歉 我习惯性地以为您这是要告诉我
Sorry. I naturally assumed that meant you were gong to tell me.
你好像一点不担心
You don't seem worried.
这种事随时都有 不归我们管
It happens all the time. It's not our problem.
暴力抢劫也不归我们 你也不在乎?
So does robbery with violence. Doesn't that worry you?
不 大臣 内政部的事
No, Minister. Home Office problem.
汉弗莱 我们把致命武器给了恐怖分子
Humphrey, we're letting terrorists have murderous weapons!
我们没有      那谁给的?
We're not. Well, who is?
天晓得 经贸部 国防部 外交部?
Trade? Ministry of Defence? Foreign Office?
是我们 汉弗莱 英国政府
We, Humphrey, the British government.
无辜的生命正受恐怖分子的英国武器威胁
Innocent lives set at risk by British arms in the hands of terrorists.
意大利人的命 不是英国的 大臣
Only Italian lives, not British lives, Minister.
也有英国游客      游客 外交部的事
Could be British tourists abroad. Tourists? Foreign Office problem.
汉弗莱 我们得采取行动
Humphrey, we have to do something.
恕我直言 大臣 我们得按兵不动
With respect, we have to do nothing.
怎么讲?      对外军售
What do you mean? The sale of arms abroad
是政府中不该细究的问题
Is one area of government we do not examine too closely.
不行 我都知道了      说您不知道
I have to, now I know. Say you don't know.
你说我不能捅?      大臣 不是说您
Are you suggesting I lie? Not you, Minister, no.
那谁不能捅?      马蜂窝不能捅 大臣
Well, who should lie? Sleeping dogs, Minister.
我得提出来      不行 大臣 我求您
I'm gong to raise this. No, I beg you.
政府原则之一就是没必要管的事不要管
A rule of government is never look into anything you don't have to,
若不能预知结果 不要展开调查
never start an enquiry unless you know what its findings will be.
真不敢相信 这是正义与邪恶问题
I can't believe this! We're talking about good and evil.
圣公会的事      不 汉弗莱
Church of England problem. No, Humphrey!
我们的事 关系到大是大非
Our problem. We are discussing right and wrong.
您也许是 跟我无关 这是浪费公务时间
I'm not. It's misuse of government time.
卖军火给恐怖分子不对 你不懂吗 汉弗莱?
Selling arms to terrorists is wrong.
不 大臣 军火要么卖要么不卖
Either you sell arms or you don't.
卖的话 总会落到出钱的人手里
If you sell them, they end up with people who can afford them.
恐怖分子不行吧?
But not terrorists?
我想我们可以
I suppose we could put
在枪托上贴政府健康警示
a government health warning on the rifle butts!
"枪支严重损害健康"
"This gun can seriously damage your health."
你可能不在乎 汉弗莱 可我们不能忽视
You may take this lightly, but we cannot close our eyes
这种重大道德错误
to something as morally wrong as this.
好吧 大臣 如果您非要谈道德问题
If you insist on discussing moral issues,
请容我指出 道德只有对与错
something is either morally wrong or it isn’t.
没有小错和大错
It can't be slightly morally wrong.
别绕弯子 汉弗莱      政府不追求道德
Don't quibble. Government isn’t about morality.
是吗 那追求什么?      稳定 社会正常运转
Really? What is it about? Stability. Keeping things gong.
预防混乱 制止分裂 屹立不倒
Stopping society falling to bits. Still being here tomorrow.
为了什么?      您说什么?
What for? I beg your pardon?
如果政府不行善 那它的目的是什么?
What is the purpose of government if not for doling good?
大臣 政府不关乎善与恶 只关乎治与乱
Government isn’t about good and evil. It's about order or chaos.
意大利恐怖分子用英国炸弹还不乱?
It's in order for Italian terrorists to get British bombs?
你不在乎?      职责不要求我在乎
You don't care? it’s not my job to care.
那是政客的事 我是执行政策的
That's what politicians are for. My job is to carry out policy.
就算你认为政策不对?      政府政策几乎都不对
If you think it’s wrong? All government policy is wrong
不过执行非常圆满
frightfully well carried out!
你有听过公务员为原则问题辞职吗?
Have you known a civil servant resign on principle?
当然没有 您怎能这么说
I should think not! What an appalling suggestion!
我第一次完全意识到了
For the first time, I fully understand
你纯粹关注手段 而非结果
that you are purely committed to means and not ends!
大臣 对我和我所有同僚来说
As far as I'm concerned, and all my colleagues,
手段和结果是一码事
there is no difference between means and ends.
你真这么以为 汉弗莱 你会下地狱的
If you believe that, Humphrey, you will go to hell.
大臣 没想到您还有神学倾向
Minister, I had no idea you had a theological bent.
你是个道德真空      这是您说的 大臣
You are a moral vacuum. If you say so, Minister.
您的午餐约会时间到了 大臣      你不吭声 伯纳
Time for your lunch appointment. You're keeping very quiet
你会怎么处理?      我会不吭声 大臣
What would you do about all this? I would keep very quiet.
大臣 那军售的事就到此为止?
So may we drop this matter of arms sales?
不 不能到此为止
No, we may not!
我要私下里通报首相
I'm gong to tell the Prime Minister personally.
给我预约 伯纳
Make an appointment, Bernard.
这种事首相一定想了解
This is the sort of thing he wants to know about.
我保证 大臣 这种事他一定不愿了解
I assure you, this is the sort of thing he wants not to know about.
我们走着瞧
We shall see about that.
那就走着瞧
Indeed we will.
怎么了 伯纳?
What's the matter, Bernard?
没事 汉弗莱爵士      你好像不开心
Nothing really, Sir Humphrey. You look unhappy.
我在想也许大臣是对的
I was wondering if the minister was right.
不大可能 哪件事?
Very unlikely. What about?
手段和目的
About ends and means.
我也会变成道德真空吗?
Will I end up as a moral vacuum, too?
我希望会的 伯纳
Oh, I hope so, Bernard.
如果你努力的话
If you work hard enough.
我觉得挺泄气的
Makes me feel rather downcast.
如果我们的工作是执行政策
If it’s our job to carry out government policies,
我们不该相信它们吗?
shouldn’t we believe in them?
哦 真是异想天开
Oh, what an extraordinary idea!
怎么?      伯纳
Why? Bernard...
我过去30年服务了11届政府
I have served 11 governments in the past 30 years.
如果我相信所有那些政策
If I'd believed in all their policies,
我会强烈反对加入共同市场
I'd have been committed to keep out of Common Market,
又强烈同意加入共同市场
and passionately committed to joining it.
我会坚信钢铁应该国营
convinced of the rightness of nationalising steel
并且私营 并且收归国营
and of denationalising it and renationalising it.
死刑呢?
Capital punishment?
我会热烈支持保留 又强烈要求废止
I'd have been a fervent retentionist and an ardent abolitionist.
我会追随凯恩斯主义 以及弗里德曼主义
I'd have been a Keynesian and a Friedmanite,
主张保留并取消文法学校
a grammar school preserver and destroyer,
狂热于国有化 醉心于私有化
a nationalisation freak and a privatisation maniac,
不过总之 我会语无伦次 并且精神分裂
I would have been a stark-staring raving schizophrenic!
那您相信什么?
So what do we believe in?
眼下 伯纳 我们相信要阻止大臣
At this moment, Bernard, we believe in stopping the minister
去通报首相
from informing the Prime Minister.
可为什么?      因为一旦首相知道了
But why? Because once the Prime Minister knows,
就得展开调查 就像水门事件
there will have to be an enquiry, like Watergate.
一个小泄密牵出一连串恐怖的大事件
A trivial break-In led to one ghastly revelation after another
终于倒下了一位总统
and finally the downfall of a president.
这是条铁律 不要去揭烂疮疤
The golden rule is don't lift lids off cans of worms.
是 汉弗莱爵士      "事物是普遍联系的"
No, Sir Humphrey. Everything is connected to everything else.
谁的名言?      内阁秘书?
Who said that? The Cabinet Secretary
差不多了 其实是列宁
Nearly right. Actually, it was Lenin.
怎样阻止内阁大臣找上首相?
How do you stop a Cabinet Minister talking to a Prime Minister?
问得好 你来说      我不知道
Interesting question. You tell me. I don't know.
想办法 伯纳 你不是前途无量嘛
Work it out. You're supposed to be a high-flier.
还是前途有量 推一步才动一步?
Or a low-flier supported by occasional gusts of wind?
您不能阻止大臣见首相 对吧?
Well, you can't stop the minister seeing the PM, can you?
我不能      首相私人办公室也不能
I can't. Nor can the private office at No. 10.
正确      必须找个高层人士
Correct. It must be someone high up in government.
思路不错      接近首相的
Getting warmer. Someone close to the PM.
能吓倒大臣们的...
Someone who can frighten the minister...
总组织秘书?      漂亮 你学到了不少
The Chief Whip? Excellent, you've learnt a lot.
那要怎么组织呢?      什么?
So, how do you crack the whip? I'm sorry
怎样才能发动组织秘书?
How do you mobilise the Chief Whip?
大臣要我给首相私人办公室打电话预约
I'm to phone the PM's private office for an appointment,
所以如果您跟内阁秘书打个招呼
so if you had a word with the Cabinet Secretary,
他跟日程秘书打个招呼
and he had a word with the diary secretary,
他俩都跟组织秘书办公室打个招呼
and they all had a word with the Whip’s office...
那么等大臣到那里
then when the minister arrived,
组织秘书可以告诉他首相很忙
the Whip could meet him and say the PM is busy
让他来接待大臣
and asked him to have a word with the minister instead.
漂亮 伯纳
Excellent, Bernard.
你应该去学工程
You should have taken a degree in engineering!
你干什么?      您不是要找内阁秘书嘛
What are you doling? You wanted the Cabinet Secretary.
我是要找 不过你作为大臣私人秘书
I do, indeed. Now, do you, as the minister's private secretary,
觉得要把刚才的对话通报大臣吗?
feel obliged to tell the minister of this conversation?
什么对话?
What conversation?
很好 伯纳 你一定能成为道德真空的
Well done, Bernard. You'll be a moral vacuum yet!
(首相办公室)
啊 吉姆
Ah, Jim.
老朋友 见到你真高兴
My dear chap, how nice to see you.
维克 我是来找首相的
Vic, I was hoping to see the Prime Minister.
对
Yes.
首相今天很忙 要我来接待你
The PM's rather busy today. Asked me to see you instead.
抱歉 维克 这不是组织秘书的事
Vic, it’s not a matter for the Chief Whip.
对 首相要我了解情况 写个背景摘要
The PM asked me to write a background note.
给他省时间
Save time later.
好吧 我听到些很耸动的消息
Well, I've been given some pretty dramatic information.
接着说
Go on.
意大利恐怖分子能够得到
The Italian Red Terrorists are being supplied
顶级机密的炸弹引爆器
with top secret bomb detonators
我国制造的 产自政府工厂
made in this country, in a government factory.
你觉得应该告诉首相?
You should tell the PM?
对 首相也负责国家安全
Yes, the PM's head of security.
我不觉得这需要麻烦首相 到此为止吧
I don't think it’s anything to burden the PM with. Let's hold it over.
你说全忘掉?      这是我的建议
Forget all about it? That's my recommendation.
抱歉 维克 我不同意 必须通报首相
I'm sorry, Vic, I can't accept it. The PM must be told.
如果首相知道 就必须展开调查      对
If the PM is told, there'd have to be an enquiry.
可能揭露出其他不良的 甚至恶劣的政府
Perhaps revealing other undesirable, even hostile, governments
也买到了英国军火
had been supplied with British-made arms.
真的?
Seriously?
可能吧 会让内阁同僚们很难堪
Might be highly embarrassing to our Cabinet colleagues,
外交大臣 国防大臣 经贸大臣 还有首相本人
Defence Secretary, Trade Secretary, and to the PM personally.
对 有时候坚持正义会很难堪
Doling the right thing might be embarrassing sometimes,
那也不能就不坚持了
but that's no reason for not doling it.
你知道也卖给叙利亚 智利 伊朗吧?
You know we already sell arms to Syria, Chile, Iran?
对 官方批准的      对 你赞成他们的用法?
it’s officially approved. You like what they do with them?
显然 不完全赞成
Well, obviously not entirely.
军火生意要么做 要么不做
Either you're in the arms business or you’re not!
如果做生意是要武装恐怖分子
If being in it means arming terrorists,
我们得退出 这不道德      好 真伟大
we should be out, it’s immoral. Oh, great!
真伟大
Great!
让十万英国工人失业就很道德啰?
Is it moral to put 100,000 British workers out of a job?
出口额呢? 一年两百万 直接的
And exports, two billion a year gone, for starters.
选票呢? 你觉得政府
And votes? Where do you think the government
把军火订单下在哪里?
places those weapons contracts?
当然在边缘选区      正是
In marginal constituencies, obviously. Exactly.
我只是说我既然知道了 得告诉首相
Now that I know, the Prime Minister must be told.
为什么?      为什么?
Why? Why?
就因为你闻到了臭气
Just because you've caught something nasty,
就得把大家都熏一通吗?
why do you have to breathe over everyone?
你在内阁还满意吧?
Are you happy in the Cabinet?
当然满意      还想留在里面吗?
Yes, of course I am! Do you want to stay in it?
那不得了
Well, then?
抱歉 维克 可我有我的职责
Sorry, Vic, but there is such a thing as duty.
有时候人得听从良心
Sometimes one must follow one's conscience.
老天爷
For God’s sake!
你那点良心非得这样招摇?
Must you flash about your petty little conscience?
你觉得别人都没良心吗?
Don't you think anybody else has got one?
你对政府存亡有没有良心?
Have you no conscience for the government?
当然有
Of course!
首相就要签署一个国际反恐公约了
The PM is signing an international anti-terrorist agreement.
我不知道      你不知道的多了
I didn’t know. There's a lot you don't know.
你就不明白 维护大政方针 比出口
Can't you see it’s essential to deal with major policy
几支小枪给恐怖分子重要得多吗?
rather than a few arms exporters and terrorists?
对 肯定的 几小股恐怖分子
Yes, I suppose it is just a couple of terrorist groups.
杀不了多少人 是吧?      肯定的
Can't kill that many people, can they? Suppose not!
而你想以道德泛滥把这一切都淹掉
And you want to blow it all in a fit of moral self-Indulgence!
再说 既然首相考虑让你接掌外交部
The PM thinking about you as the next Foreign Secretary
你说真的?
Do you mean that?
老天啊
Good Lord!
你想壮烈牺牲的话 去展开调查好了
So if you want to martyr yourself, go for an enquiry.
尽情毁掉我们奋斗几年的成果吧
Feel free to jeopardise everything we've worked for all these years.
不不 这确实很可怕
No, no. Obviously it’s appalling
意大利恐怖分子拿到了英国军火
If Italian terrorists are getting hold of British weapons,
可你说了 为了保持忠诚 顾全大局
but there is such a thing as loyalty, the common purpose.
我想这个问题必须正确看待
I suppose one must see these things in a proper perspective.
如果关系到国防部 经贸部
If it was the Ministry of Defence, Board of Trade.
对对 国防部的事 经贸部的事
Ministry of Defence, Board of Trade problem.
外交部的事 这下我明白了
Foreign Office problem. I can see that now.
那我们就暂时到此为止?
So we can hold it over for the time being?
总不能让首相心烦或者难堪嘛
Don’t want to upset and embarrass the PM!
当然不行 绝对不行 对
Absolutely not. Definitely not. No.
真抱歉我提出来
Sorry I mentioned it.
你不错
Good man!
所以我权衡之后 觉得还是不管的好
So I thought on balance It was best to leave it at that.
马蜂窝不能捅
Let sleeping dogs lie...
为了大家好
in the wilder interest.
做忠诚的政府官员
As a loyal member of the government.
揭烂疮疤没什么好处
Nothing to be gained. Opening a can of worms.
可少校说他们是恐怖分子
The major said they were terrorists.
对 可是...
Yes, well...
我们也轰炸德累斯顿 大家都是恐怖分子
We bombed Dresden. We're all terrorists.
不是
No.
我就打个比方
I mean metaphorically.
你该见见组织秘书 他绝对是
You should meet the Chief Whip. He certainly is!
可英国有人送炸弹给刽子手
Someone in Britain’s giving bombs to murderers.
是卖 不是送
Selling, not giving.
那就有理啦?      说真的 安妮
That makes it Ok? Be serious, Annie.
发起调查可能牵出别的事
An investigation might uncover all sorts.
懂了 一人犯法就展开调查
I see. Investigate If you can catch one criminal,
众人犯法就得捂盖子
but not if you might catch lots!
如果这些人是你内阁同僚 就得捂
If they're your Cabinet colleagues, you're right!
政府运作很复杂的 安妮
Government is a very complex business, Annie.
到处都是矛盾冲突
There are so many conflicting considerations.
比如是做正确的事呢 还是犯错
Whether to do the right thing or wrong thing.
正是 不...
Exactly. No...
你要我怎么办?
What do you suggest I do?
捍卫道德原则      怎么捍卫?
Take a moral stand. How
以辞职威胁      他们会接受的
Threaten resignation. They'd accept it!
然后我去哪?
Then where would I be?
要是我下了台 就再也做不了好事了
If I'm gone, I'm not in a position to do any good any more.
你现在也没做好事嘛
You're not doling good now.
辞职只能安慰你我的良心
Resignation may be a sop to our consciences,
不能阻止意大利恐怖分子用英国炸弹
but it won’t stop terrorists getting British bombs.
可以把你知道的公开啊      我知道什么?
It might if you tell what you know. What do I know
我没有证据 我知道有这回事
I've no hard facts. I know it’s gong on
因为没人否认 但这不是证据
because nobody's denied it, but that's not proof.
你看不出吗? 我进退两难
Can't you see? I'm in a real fix.
我看你还没意识到你有多难
I don't think you realise just how real a fix you're in.
这封信今天到的
This letter arrived today.
桑德斯少校写的
From Major Saunders.
"亲爱的哈克先生 多谢接见我"
"Dear Mr Hacker. Thank you for seeing me.
"我如释重负 我已经告诉您"
Such a relief to have told you about the supply
"英国武器卖给意大利恐怖分子的事"
of British weapons to Italian terrorists.
"相信您会信守承诺 采取行动"
I know you will act upon this information as you promised
"热切期待看到您的对策"
and I look forward to seeing some action taken."
你瞧
You see?
傻眼了吧 桑德斯少校可以昭告天下
What will you do when Major Saunders tells the world
说他通报给了你 你无动于衷
he told you about it and you did nothing?
这是复印件 原件在他那
It's a photocopy. He's got the original.
是挂号信 你还不能说没收到
It was recorded delivery, so you did get it.
我上钩了
I'm trapped!
完全上钩了
Completely trapped!
不能告诉首相 也不能不告诉首相
I can't tell the PM, I can't not tell the PM.
明白了
I see.
大臣 不能用罗德西亚(津巴布韦)办法吗?
Might we not use the Rhodesia Solution?
伯纳 你太有长进了
Bernard, you excel yourself!
当然 大臣 罗德西亚办法
Of course, Minister, the Rhodesia Solution!
那是什么?      石油制裁的事
What's that? Oil sanctions.
有人告诉某政府要员 英国公司在破坏制裁
A member of the government was told about sanction-busting.
他怎么办?      通报首相
What did he do? Told the PM.
他用首相听不见的方法告诉首相
He told the PM in a way the PM didn’t hear him.
哦 你要我在投票厅里咕哝一句?
Oh. Do you mean I should mumble it in the Division lobby?
不 大臣 写个便条      用浅色铅笔?
No, Minister, you write a note. Very faint pencil?
请具体些      大臣 显而易见
Please, be practical. it’s awfully obvious.
您要写张容易被误解的便条
Write a note susceptible of misinterpretation.
哦 是吗
Oh, I see!
"亲爱的首相 我发现意大利恐怖分子"
"Dear Prime Minister, I believe Italian Red Terrorists
"能拿到英国机密炸弹引爆器"
have secret British bomb-making equipment."
这要怎么误解?
How do you misinterpret that?
没法误解 所以不这样写
You can't. So you don't write that.
风格要慎重 不提炸弹或恐怖分子
Circumspect style with no mention of bombs or terrorists.
这就难了 还能剩下什么?      伯纳 记下来
Isn't that what it’s all about? Bernard, write this down.
"最近我私下里得知一些消息"
"My attention has been drawn to information
"显示可能有人违反..."
which suggests possible irregularities under..."
"1939(丙)进出口和海关权力法案第一条"
Section 1 of the Export Powers Defence Act 1939c.
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard.
然后您说 别的什么人得采取措施
Somebody else should do something about it.
"证据显示也许有必要进一步了解"
"Evidence suggests there may be a case for further investigation
"以便决定是否要展开调查"
to establish whether enquires should be put in hand."
然后你再放个烟幕
Then you smudge it all over.
"然而必须强调 已知情报有限"
"It should be stressed that available information is limited
"事实难以切实确立和把握"
and facts could be difficult to establish with any certainty."
懂了      就算展开调查 您也清白无辜
If there's an enquiry, you'd be in the clear
谁都理解日理万机的首相
and everybody would understand the busy PM
也许没听出暗示
might not have grasped the implications.
当然听不出 太含糊了      谢谢 大臣
They certainly would! That's most unclear. Thank you, Minister!
然后 您送这封信到十号
You arrange for the letter to arrive at No. 10
要在首相出国参加首脑峰会前夕
on the day the PM has an overseas summit!
于是又搞不清是首相
So there is also doubt about whether it was the PM
还是代理首相读到它
or the acting PM who read the note.
这样联络就切断了
It's seen as a breakdown in communication,
人人都清白 可以各行其是了
everyone's cleared and can get on with things.
包括恐怖分子      没错...伯纳
Including the Red Terrorists! Exactly... Bernard!
告诉你政府怎么回事
I'll tell you about government.
你总得做对的事
You must always try to do the right thing.
可是不能叫人发现
But you must never let anybody catch you trying to do it
因为做对就是做错 对吧?
because doling right’s wrong. Right?
别喝了吧 亲爱的      还没见底呢
You had enough, darling? There's left in the bottle.
不 政府要的是原则
No, the thing about government Is principle.
原则就是你不能捅马蜂窝...
And the principle Is you mustn't rock the boat...
不然会害到一堆小小的良心
because if you do, all the little consciences will fall out.
你们必须扯在一根绳上
And you must all hang together.
不然就会被分头吊死 (富兰克林)
Because if you don't hang together, you'll all be hanged separately.
我不扯着他们就得吊死
I'm hanged if I'll be hanged!
告诉你 搞政治就是要帮助别人
You know... politics is about helping others.
就算帮的是恐怖分子
Even if that means helping terrorists.
恐怖分子也是别人吧 不是我们自己吧
Terrorists are others, aren't they? Not us, are they?
不是
No.
而且你得时刻跟着良心走
And you must always follow your conscience,
不过也得知道你要朝哪走
but you must know where you're gong.
所以不能总跟着良心
So you can't follow your conscience.
因为它可能不跟你往一块走
'Cause it may not be gong the same way that you are.
干了...就像我
Empty... Like me.
我也是道德真空      开心点 亲爱的
I'm a moral vacuum. Cheer up, darling!
白厅里出不了好东西 你已经尽力了
Nothing good comes out of Whitehall. You did what you could.
你不是说真的      是真的
You don't really mean that. I do.
我跟汉弗莱他们一回事      绝对不是
I'm just like Humphrey and the rest. That's not true!
他的是非观已经没有了 你还有
He's lost his sense of right and wrong. You've still got yours.
有吗?      只是不常用罢了
Have I? it’s just that you don't use it much.
你就像个酒鬼牧师
You're a sort of whisky priest,
你犯错的时候 至少明知是错的
you at least know when you've done the wrong thing.
酒鬼牧师      是啊
Whisky priest? That's right.
好
Good.
我们再开一瓶      家里没有了
Let's open another bottle. We haven't got one.
那是你以为
That's what you think!
谁说白厅出不了好东西?
Who said nothing good ever came out of Whitehall?
你也来一杯?      是 大臣
You want one? Yes, Minister